Your browser either does not have JavaScript enabled or does not appear to support enough features of JavaScript to be used well on this site.

* [Teams](javascript:void(0))

### PRIVACY POLICY

Published 30/07/2018 12.32 PM   |    Updated 23/05/2023 03.14 PM

Australian Red Cross Lifeblood (Lifeblood) is bound by the Privacy Act 1988 as well as other laws that impose obligations regarding personal and health information. Lifeblood is committed to protecting the privacy of personal and health information.  
  
This Privacy Policy details how your personal information is collected, used, stored and disclosed by Lifeblood and how you may contact us if you would like to access or correct your personal information.

This Privacy Policy sets out Australian Red Cross Lifeblood’s (Lifeblood) commitment to protecting the privacy of personal information, including health information, collected by Lifeblood or provided to Lifeblood, both tangibly (e.g.  in person at donor centres) or online (e.g. through Lifeblood websites, mobile applications or other digital platforms).  

This Privacy Policy details how personal information is collected, used, stored and disclosed by Lifeblood and your rights in relation to this.

What personal information Lifeblood collected and holds
-------------------------------------------------------

In order to provide life-giving blood, plasma, transplantation and biological products for world-leading health outcomes, Lifeblood collects and holds personal information about individuals (including sensitive health information).

#### Blood Donors 

For the safety of both donors and the blood supply,  Lifeblood needs to collect information about health, medical history, travel and certain high risk activities (in the context of blood donation) of blood donors and people volunteering to be blood donors.  The information collected from blood donors includes:

* Name
* Contact details including email address, mailing  address, street address and telephone numbers
* Date of birth
* Medical history
* Travel history
* Certain high risk behaviours relevant to a safe blood supply, such as recent sexual activity

Lifeblood will collect and hold the personal information supplied by donors when they register, or attend Lifeblood as a donor including in the donor interview, test results for each donation, details of any adverse events and any communication or correspondence with individual donors.

From time to time Lifeblood may also collect personal information from donors or prospective donors through customer surveys.

#### Recipients of blood products

From time to time, Australian health service providers provide Lifeblood with details of recipients (including potential recipients) of blood products.  

This information may include the recipient’s name, blood type, test results and other health information.

#### Medical Pathology Services – Transplantations and Immunogenetics and Red Cell Reference

Personal information relevant to these services is not collected directly from an individual but is passed to the Lifeblood Tissue Typing Service via referral from the individuals treating health service provider.

This information could include:

* Name 
* Date of birth 
* Address, postal and email, and telephone numbers 
* Medical history, current medication and other clinical information  
* Emergency contact details 
* Health fund and health insurance details 
* Medicare number

The personal information provided to Lifeblood meets the requirements for Medical Pathology Services (NPAAC guidelines). 

More information about medical pathologies services [is available online](https://www.lifeblood.com.au/about/our-services).

#### Research participants 

The Lifeblood conducts research regarding blood donation and transfusion. Sometimes de-identified donation information, such as age and gender, may be used for that research.  Research on donor behaviour using both donor and non-donor participants is conducted where consent is obtained from the individual.

Before research is undertaken in relation to any part of a blood donation, approval from an appropriate Human Research Ethics Committee is required and obtained by Lifeblood. 

#### Website visitors 

Lifeblood may collect the following information about visitors to Lifeblood websites or users of Lifeblood mobile applications:

* Additional personal information provided directly or indirectly through the use of the website, associated applications, associated social media platforms and or accounts from which users (including donors, recipients, health professionals and members of the public) permit us to collect information.
* Browser session and geo-location data, device and network information, statistics on page views and sessions, acquisition sources, search queries and browsing behaviour.
* Information about access and use of our website, including through the use of internet cookies, communications with our website, type of browser used, type of operating system used and domain name of internet service provider.

Why we collect personal information and what we use it for
----------------------------------------------------------

Lifeblood will use your personal information for:

* the primary purposes for which it was collected (as set out below); or
* for secondary purposes directly related to the primary purposes for which it was collected which you would reasonably expect; or
* for other purposes that Lifeblood has told the relevant individual’s about; or 
* as permitted or required by law.

#### Blood Donors

Personal information is collected from and used by Lifeblood for the following purposes:

* to assess the eligibility of individuals to donate blood and to protect both donor health and safety and the safety and sufficiency of blood and blood products;
* to maintain contact with donors regarding past donations and for the purposes of future donations;
* for research, including research regarding and research for the purposes of therapeutic benefit  blood transfusion and blood safety; and
* to maintain contact with donors for the purposes of research, including market research, regarding blood donation and collection and participation in Lifeblood activities.

Lifeblood also uses information collected from blood donors:

* for internal record keeping and administrative purposes such as risk management, education and training of staff, quality assurance activities and to monitor donor satisfaction; and
* to comply with its legal obligations including under the Therapeutic Goods Act and health record laws

#### Recipients of blood products

In order to provide the most appropriate blood product, Australian health service providers from time to time provide Lifeblood with details of recipients of blood products.  This information is held for future use in the event of further transfusion needs to assist in timely supply of appropriate blood products.

#### Medical Pathology Services – Transplantations and Immunogenetics and Red Cell Reference

The personal information collected by Lifeblood meets the requirements for Medical Pathology Services (NPAAC guidelines). The information is used to generate clinical reports which are provided to the appropriate health service providers directly involved in the individual’s clinical care for organ and stem cell transplant or immunogenetics testing. 

#### Research participants 

Lifeblood conducts world-class research to inform core activities and contribute to improved operational procedures and changes in clinical practice. Information from blood donors and other research participants is used to conduct this research.

#### Website visitors 

Information from visitors to Lifeblood websites may be used:

* for data analytics, market research and business development, including to operate and improve our website, associated applications and associated social media platforms;
* for online transfusion education programs run for health professionals;
* to send individuals tailored information about blood donation and Lifeblood.

Disclosure of your personal information
---------------------------------------

Lifeblood may disclose your personal information to:

* Lifeblood employees whose job responsibilities require such access;
* third party service providers for the purpose of enabling them to provide their services, including Australian health service providers where information is relevant for recipient care/clinical safety, IT service provides, data storage, webhosting and server providers, marketing or advertising provider;
* our insurers, but only to the extent necessary and permitted by law;
* courts, tribunals, regulatory authorities and law enforcement officers as required by law, in connection with any actual or prospective legal proceedings, or in order to establish, exercise or defend our legal rights;
* third parties, including professional colleges and societies, agents or sub-contractors, who assist us in providing information, products, services or communications to you.  This may include parties located, or that store data, outside of Australia;
* third parties to collect and process data on behalf of Lifeblood, such as Google Analytics. This may include parties located, or that store data, outside of Australia.

If Lifeblood provides your details to a third party acting on behalf ofLifeblood, the third party will be subject to a confidentiality agreement and must only use your personal information for the purposes for which it was provided.  They will be subject to privacy standards equivalent to those that Lifeblood is required to comply with.

Lifeblood will not use sensitive information, including health information, for any direct marketing.

Lifeblood will not sell your personal information.

Your rights and controlling your personal information
-----------------------------------------------------

#### Consent

Please read this Privacy Policy carefully.  By providing personal information to us, you consent to us collecting, holding, using and disclosing your personal information in accordance with this Privacy Policy.

#### Access and correction

You have a right to request access to your own personal information.  You also have a right to request its correction if you consider it is incorrect. 

In order to protect your personal information from being disclosed to the wrong person, Lifeblood has processes in place to ensure that your identity is confirm as well as the information that you are requesting.

The process for requesting your personal information that Lifeblood holds is as follows:

* complete the form - [download privacy request form](https://www.lifeblood.com.au/sites/default/files/resource-library/2023-05/request-for-access-to-personal-information-v8.0.pdf)
* provide the form and a copy of a form of proof of identity to either:
    * Chief Privacy Officer, GPO Box 5103, Melbourne, Victoria 3001; or

Once Lifeblood receives the form and confirms your identity the proof of identity will be deleted or destroyed.

Lifeblood seeks to deal with requests promptly but the time to respond can vary depending upon the information requested and the number of requests received. If you can be as specific as possible about the information requested this assists in collating and providing the information.

If you believe any personal information we are holding is incorrect or incomplete please contact the Chief Privacy Officer at either:

* GPO Box 5103, Melbourne, Victoria 3001; or

#### Anonymity

You can contact Lifeblood anonymously online or by calling 1300 606 833.  In some cases, Lifeblood may not be able to provide further information without verifying your identity.

#### Information from third parties

If Lifeblood receives information about you from a third party, Lifeblood will protect that information as set out in this Privacy Policy. Lifeblood only seeks to collect information from someone else if you have consented, it is authorised or required by law, or if it is unreasonable or impracticable to collect that information from you. 

#### Unsubscribe

To unsubscribe from Lifeblood’s email database or opt out of communications please contact Lifeblood using the details below or opt-out using the opt-out facilities provided in the communication.

Complaints
----------

If you believe that Lifeblood has breached the Australian Privacy Principles and wish to make a complaint, please contact Lifeblood setting out the details of the alleged breach, at either:

* Chief Privacy Officer, GPO Box 5103, Melbourne, Victoria 3001; or

Your complaint will be promptly investigated and Lifeblood will respond to you, in writing, setting out the outcome of the investigation and the steps Lifeblood has taken or will take to deal with your complaint. 

If you are not satisfied with Lifeblood’s response you can refer your complaint to the Office of Australian Information Commissioner.

Storage and retention
---------------------

Lifeblood is committed to ensuring that the personal information it collects is secure.  In order to prevent unauthorised access or disclosure Lifeblood has put in place suitable physical, electronic and managerial procedures to safeguard and secure the personal information and protect it from misuse, interference, loss and unauthorised access, modification and disclosure.

In order to administer, secure and back-up your personal information, your personal information may be transferred, stored, disclosed, or processed in data centres located outside Australia, including the United States of America, Singapore and  other jurisdictions from time to time.

Where information is stored by a third party, Lifeblood requires them to comply with the Privacy Act and our Privacy Policy. This compliance will be monitored by Lifeblood.

Under Therapeutic Goods Legislation Lifeblood maintains blood donor records for as long as reasonably required for the purposes of the safety of donors and recipients. 

Collection, use and disclosure of personal information through Lifeblood's website
----------------------------------------------------------------------------------

When you email Lifeblood with a query, Lifeblood will collect the personal information you provide. Subject to any exceptions within the privacy legislation, Lifeblood will not use or disclose this information for any purpose other than to progress and respond to your query. 

Lifeblood may use cookies on our websites from time to time. Cookies are text files placed in your computers browser to store your preferences.  Cookies, by themselves, do not tell Lifeblood your email address or other personally identifiable information.  However, they do allow third parties, such as Google and Facebook, to cause Lifeblood advertisements to appear on your social media and online media feeds as part of Lifeblood targeting campaigns.  If and when you choose to provide Lifeblood websites with personal information, this information may be linked to data stored in the cookie.

Lifeblood may use web beacons on our websites from time to time. Web beacons (also knowns as Clear GIFs) are small pieces of code placed on a web page to monitor the visitor’s behaviour and collect data about the visitor’s viewing of a web page.  For example, web beacons can be used to count the users who visit a web page or to deliver a cookie to the browser of a visitor viewing the page.

Overseas disclosure
-------------------

Lifeblood will not disclose personal information to an overseas entity except in circumstances where it is permitted under the Privacy Act 1988 (Cth). However, please note information about overseas storage in the “Storage and Retention” section above.

Applications for employment
---------------------------

Personal information provided to Lifeblood for the purposes of seeking employment is collected and used only for the purposes of considering your application.  The ‘Australian Red Cross Lifeblood Recruitment Privacy Statement’ is provided to all applicants and contains a description of how information will be collected, used and stored.

Review and amendments
---------------------

Lifeblood may, at any time, vary this Privacy Policy by publishing an amended Privacy Policy on its websites.  It is recommend that you check the Lifeblood website regularly to ensure you are aware of the current Privacy Policy. 

This Privacy Policy will be reviewed by Lifeblood at least every 2 years or more frequently if required by the Privacy Act or other relevant legislation.

[Email this page](javascript:void(0); "Email a link to this answer")

Recipient Email \*  Your Email \*  Your Name \* 

[Print](javascript:void(0); "Print this page")

[Share](javascript:void(0); "Share this page on social networks")

Is this answer helpful?
-----------------------

Yes No

Most viewed questions
---------------------

* [Sexual activity - Is there any sexual activity that will affect my ability to donate blood?](https://my.donateblood.com.au/app/answers/detail/a_id/32/related/1/session/L2F2LzEvdGltZS8xNzI5MTkxMjY1L2dlbi8xNzI5MTkxMjY1L3NpZC9mVTBUVndxcjVtVVNiYjRmOTkwJTdFQ0tGWDMlN0UxJTdFVDJOVTI4T205eFY3aXl2MWhkQTg0N0lYUUdBWDJ0N19aQm4zdDQ2blVJNWYlN0VRYlFjJTdFd29hd3BaVHRTNEllbWRrU1VlZFVEREpkTEElN0VnJTdFS0Zfb0JCVW4lN0VUbUFnJTIxJTIx)
* [Iron (low) - Can I donate if my iron levels are low (iron deficiency) and/or my haemoglobin levels are low (anaemia)?](https://my.donateblood.com.au/app/answers/detail/a_id/22/related/1/session/L2F2LzEvdGltZS8xNzI5MTkxMjY1L2dlbi8xNzI5MTkxMjY1L3NpZC9mVTBUVndxcjVtVVNiYjRmOTkwJTdFQ0tGWDMlN0UxJTdFVDJOVTI4T205eFY3aXl2MWhkQTg0N0lYUUdBWDJ0N19aQm4zdDQ2blVJNWYlN0VRYlFjJTdFd29hd3BaVHRTNEllbWRrU1VlZFVEREpkTEElN0VnJTdFS0Zfb0JCVW4lN0VUbUFnJTIxJTIx)

Together, we're  
Australia's Lifeblood.

Lifeblood acknowledges and pays our respect to the past, present and future Traditional Custodians and Elders of this nation and the continuation of cultural, spiritual and educational practices of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander peoples.

© 2024 Australian Red Cross Lifeblood
